In this lesson we're going to require users to authenticate before they can see the
dashboard that we're working on. To do that, we're going to use an
Open Authentication strategy, or "Oauth", to log users into our
application. If you're not familiar with Oauth
please check the lesson notes for a thorough explanation.
Today, we're going to use the Omniauth gem and an Oauth strategy gem to allow users
to authenticate via DigitalOcean's Oauth service.
At the bottom of our gemfile we'll add Omniauth and Omniauth-digitalocean
gems, each fixed to a specific version.
Then, we'll bundle install.
Before we start writing any code, you may remember that
in our last lesson we added Cucumber to our project so we could follow a test-first
method, also known as Behavior-Driven-Development or BDD.
So, let's write the feature scenario that we need to cover for the
most basic authentication requirements.
In the features directory, create a file named authentication.feature
In it, write the following: "In order to protect sensitive information
as a user, I should log in before accessing my dashboard"
Scenario: unauthenticated request to a dashboard
"Given I am not logged in. When I visit
the root URL then the response should be the login page"
Now, run the "bundle exec cucumber" command.
Cucumber gives us the recommended step definitions.
Copy those and put them into a file named authentication.rb
inside the features/step_definitions directory.
So, what does it mean for a user
to not be logged in? For our application
a user is not logged in if they have no active session id.
Because by default a user has no active session ID, the first step definition
can remain blank. Now the second definition is simple.
We just need to have a login page. Our bootstrap theme actually came with a
login page. So, let's use it.
The sample login page is simple
and has very little text. The "Please Sign In" text looks unique
enough for us to use for our test's target.
That means, in this step we can, expect
the page to have content
"Please Sign In". Ok, running
the scenarios with "bundle exec cucumber" - one fails, as expected
because we don't have a login page.
Create a sessions_controller.rb in app/controllers
it will inherit for ApplicationController and will have a single method
"new".
Save it. Then create a directory named "sessions" in app/views
In there, we'll create a new.html.erb file and copy in all the body
content from the bootstrap theme's login.html.
Be sure not to copy the javascript references, though.
We already included those in a previous lesson.
We'll make one edit to this template. Since we'll be doing Oauth
via DigitalOcean, we need a nice logo on here that people can click
to authenticate. This logo is available in the lesson notes so just
add the file to your app/assets/images directory.
Then, right above the existing HTML form tag
insert a link with this logo.
The href for this link is pointing at a route that the omniauth gem provides
our rails application. After adding that logo
comment out the regular login form, since we don't need it right now,
and save that file. After reading
the omniauth documentation, I know that we'll need these specific routes.
GET auth/new, GET auth/provider/callback
GET auth/logout
and GET auth/failure. We'll route each them to our SessionsController.
Auth/new will go to SessionsController new method.
And auth/provider/callback will go to a create method
in SessionsController. While the auth/logout route will point
to the SessionsController destroy, and auth/failure will point
to "sessions#failure". We didn't actually add
the "create", "failure", and destroy methods to the controller yet. So let's
go back and add those now. In app/controllers/sessions_controller.rb
add those 3 blank methods.
Make sure you save both the controller and the routes file.
Now, let's do the minimum necessary to pass our scenario.
All we have to do is redirect to the login page for this to pass.
We'll do that using a before_filter in application controller.
In app/controllers/application_controller.rb
named "verify_session" then add it to the before filters.
We want this method to redirect to the login page.
We can find the route to the login page by opening a terminal and typing:
"bundle exec rake routes"
There we see that the path to "sessions#new" is the auth_new path.
So this method should just redirect to the "auth_new" path.
Save the application_controller.
Since we added this before_filter in application_controller
it will apply to all controllers that inherit from it.
To prevent an infinite redirect loop, we need to add
a skip_before_filter to the SessionsController.
Now, let's run our scenarios. The output shows us
that our new scenario is now passing, but the scenario that we wrote in the previous lesson
is now failing. Since we want only authenticated users to access
the dashboard, this makes sense. But now we need to write the code
so a logged in user can access the dashboard page.
First, we'll need an initializer for Omniauth.
In config/initializers directory, create a file named
"01_omniauth.rb" and add this code.
The two placeholder strings are for your client ID and secret
token that you got from Digital Ocean. In the lesson notes on RailsMania.com
we show what you'll need to do to get those.
So be sure to check that out if you haven't gotten them yet.
I'll add my client ID and secret token then save this file.
Ok, now it's time to hook everything up. Basically, we want a user to click
the login logo, authenticate with Digital Ocean, then redirect to our application.
When they redirect, they'll land on
the SessionsController create method. Here we want to find an existing
session that matches, or create a new one based on the authentication hash
as long as it has a truthy value.
And, we'll add this protected helper method.
There are 3 things that we need to cover about this code.
First, the special session hash is provided to us by Rails.
This special hash persists information between
requests. Anything that we put into it in this request will be around in
the next request assuming we don't intentionally delete it and assuming
the user doesn't delete their cookies. Second,
the request.env is another special hash provided to us by Rails.
It contains a lot of information about the current request environment.
Omniauth has placed a special payload of information there about the user
that just authenticated via our open authentication provider,
Digital Ocean. And third, we haven't yet talked about a
Session object, but in this method we're finding or creating an instance of
Session. The Session object is a model that we need to create.
We'll use it to save session information to the database for easy lookup.
So, let's create that model by opening a terminal and typing
"bundle exec rails generate model
Session content:text" followed by
"bundle exec rake db:migrate"
That created our Session model,
database migration, and then we created the table by running the migration.
Next, let's go back to our application_controller
That quick code that we wrote earlier to pass our scenario needs to be updated.
Change it to match the following.
Now we're only going to redirect to the login page if there isn't a session instance
with ID equal to the value in session[:active]
Ok, time to try it all out. Open up a terminal.
Make sure you are in your project's directory. Then start your server.
"bundle exec rails server"
Open your server's URL in your browser and
"great!" it redirected us to the login page.
Clicking the link takes us to Digital Ocean where we authenticate.
Digitial Ocean then sends us back to our application and we're logged in. Success!
This is great. Now, let's do two last things.
First, let's make this logout link work. We'll edit apps/views/dashboards/index.html.erb
to add the auth_logout_path
to that link.
We'll also update SessionsController's destroy method to properly destroy
our session when we click "logout."
"reset_session" is another thing Rails provides us. It effectively destroys
a session as far as Rails is concerned. We destroy our own session record
in the database and then redirect to the login page.
We can test this quite simply by clicking logout then trying to access the dashboard.
And, finally, when we check our scenarios
we see that one thing is still failing.
We need to get that one failing scenario to pass. Here's how.
Add a new step to the dashboard feature.
"Given I am logged in" and add this definition to our
authentication.rb file in features/step_definitions.
Then, run the scenarios.
And, now the pass as expected.
Alright, that's all we can pack into one lesson.
If you have any questions or comments, please contact us on RailsMania.com. Thanks for watching.