Today, we'll add some fundamental automated testing tools
so we can ensure we're delivering working features that do exactly what we wanted them to do.
If you're not familiar with Behavior Driven Development, often called
BDD, or Test Driven Development - I encourage you to learn more about it by
looking at this lesson's notes. In this lesson, we're going to
keep it simple so you can follow along, even if you're not familiar with BDD.
So, let's get started. First, let's open
the gemfile for the project we made in the previous lesson.
The gemfile is a list of all the non-standard Ruby libraries that your application
depends upon. As you can see, even Rails is listed in the gemfile.
At the bottom, we want to create a group
of gems that are only available to our development and test environments.
The three gems that we want to include are:
rspec-rails, cucumber-rails, and database_cleaner.
The number after each of these gems defines the precise
version we'd like to use. To ensure you have the same experience as captured
in this video lesson, be sure to lock each gem to the exact
same version as we have here. Now, let's save this file.
After modifying the gemfile, we have to tell our project to
recheck and gather any dependencies that we didn't gather previously.
So now we need to open up a console and run: bundle install.
Bundler will fetch our three new dependencies
and any dependencies that they might have and install them
for our application to use.
Once bundler has finished installing our gems, we need to complete a single installation step
that cucumber requires. Simply type:
rails generate cucumber:install. Cucumber creates the necessary files and folders
for our project and now it's time for us to verify everything is installed correctly.
To do that, let's run bundle exec rake cucumber
We don't see much at all, but at least
there are no errors. The console output does mention that there are zero
scenarios with zero steps, and that's exactly right because we haven't written any yet.
So now it's time to actually write our first scenario.
Create a file in features named dashboards.feature
In that file, we'll start with the keyword "Feature" then follow that with a single
word description. Starting with an indent on the second line
we'll type a short user story explaining what we're trying to do.
In order to see current activity, a user
should access a central dashboard.
That's what we want this feature file to test for. Now we need to write a scenario
that tests this feature. So we'll add a simple scenario
that covers the basic requirement that a user can access a central dashboard.
When I visit the root URL then the response should be
the central dashboard. That's it!
Our next step is to try rerunning the cucumber command.
In the terminal run "bundle exec rake cucumber"
This time the output is different. Cucumber attempted to run the scenario
we wrote but didn't know what commands to execute to actually complete
each step. Thankfully, cucumber suggested to us what we can use
for step definitions. So copy the suggested steps.
Create a file called dashboards.rb in features/step_definitions directory
and paste the suggested content in there.
Save that file, then run the scenarios again to see the difference.
"bundle exec rake cucumber"
This time cucumber realizes that we have step definitions but that we haven't
customized them to test exactly what we want them to test.
Now all we have to do is write a little code for testing.
In our first step we just want to visit our root path of our application.
And in the second step we want cucumber to verify
that the HTML response has some visible HTML content that
we can identify as the central dashboard.
For now we're going to say that we - expect the page to have content
"Dashboard". Let's save that file. Then run our
cucumber scenario again to make sure everything passes.
Voila! They pass. But let's make sure we're not being tricked.
Let's see if it really is testing the page's content. We can do that by
changing "Dashboard" to something we know isn't on that page like "RailsMania"
Running the tests again we see the scenario failed.
And it even printed out that it expected to find "RailsMania" but that it wasn't
found in all the visible HTML content. Great! We're all setup
to start developing this application following a Behavior Driven Development or
BDD style. In the next lesson we'll show the scenario we wrote for
our next feature before we get busy writing the code to implement it.
If you want to learn more about how Cucumber works and many of its little know features
checkout the in-depth lesson on RailsMania.com.
Thanks for watching!